<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="//purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="//purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="//www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="//search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title><![CDATA[Tutorial - Linuxed and reversed ]]></title><description><![CDATA[How-to's, Investigations, Reversing and nifty hacks]]></description><link>https://shubham0d.github.io/</link><image><url>https://shubham0d.github.io/favicon.png</url><title>Tutorial - Linuxed and reversed </title><link>https://shubham0d.github.io/</link></image><generator>Ghost 1.19</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 09:12:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://shubham0d.github.io/tag/tutorial/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite]]></title><description><![CDATA[Did your system ever get affected with malwares? Did you know you can manually remove common malwares with very little technical knowledge.
In this article I will explain you how to find malware using sysinternals suite.]]></description><link>https://shubham0d.github.io/finding-and-removing-malware-from-windows-in-minimal-steps-using-sysinternals-suite/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a48ea60ac4a8a1324eb0c45</guid><category><![CDATA[Security]]></category><category><![CDATA[Analysis]]></category><category><![CDATA[Tutorial]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Shubham Dubey]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 14:20:02 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/check-malware-script-installed-blog-FILEminimizer1.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/check-malware-script-installed-blog-FILEminimizer1.jpg" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"><p>Hello, there!<br>
<em>Did your system ever get affected with malwares?</em><br>
Probably yes!, maybe that’s why you are reading this article. And If your answer is no! Then maybe you never tried to find answers for questions like <em>whats wrong with your system?, why it is behaving different? and why  is it slow from few days?</em>. But you may argue that you never face these issues because you always use antivirus software.<br>
Well, you are partially right there. Antivirus can save you from malwares most of the time(atleast from those malwares from which most users get affected) but not always. And what if you don’t have any antivirus installed. Did you ever think that you can also manually remove common malwares with very little technical knowledge.</p>
<p>You must have guessed that I am gonna teach you that in this post. Yes! but in some extent. <em><strong>This post is more about my recent experience with malware’s on my friends computer and how did I removed them</strong>.</em> But don’t close this tab after reading this because you can use the same procedure to detect the most malwares affecting your system. Also in future articles I will explain the In-depth procedure for malware detection that you can use. But for now lets look at minimal things that you can do.</p>
<h2 id="herestartsthestory">Here starts the story</h2>
<p>Recently one of my friend complained me about his windows 8 working slow, power consumption get high from few days. Also the major issue he was facing is whenever he try to browse any site in mozilla firefox he gets error about invalid certificate and connection is not secure.</p>
<p><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/invalidcertificaate.png" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"></p>
<p>By looking at these issues I knew that something must be fishy going on in his system but I got no idea what may have causing these issues. It maybe some program that he have installed causing that or maybe some misconfiguration.</p>
<p>So, my first priroty is to fix the browser issue. Other issues are something that windows users always complain about, so I try to ignore them.<br>
I have the seen the browser issue multiple times so I was sure it must be causing due to change in proxy setting by some program(to monitor the traffic) or because of antivirus itself. So, first thing I tried is looking for current proxy setting in firefox. For that I click on right top icon on firefox and then on options from the drop down.</p>
<p><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/imageedit_2_5575992658.png" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"></p>
<p>In General tab at the bottom I found network proxy option.</p>
<p><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/proxyfirefox.png" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"></p>
<p>I was expecting it to set to some Manual proxy configuration but it is set correctly to auto detect proxy settings.</p>
<p><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/updatedproxyimage.png" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"><br>
Next step I did is to look for antivirus in his system which generally change the proxy settings. But my friend told he doesn’t have any antivirus program installed on his system(which I think maybe the root cause of problem.). So, I look for some installed program in hope that I will find some malicious program and will uninstall that. But there was nothing installed that I can tell is fishy.<br>
So, after little more struggle I decide to use sysinternals suite to look deeper into the problem.</p>
<h2 id="whataresysinternalssuite">What are sysinternals suite?</h2>
<p>Sysinternals suite(<a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/sysinternals/downloads/sysinternals-suite">link</a>) consist of utilities/tools to help you manage, troubleshoot and diagnose your Windows systems and applications. Some most common tools are process explorer, registry editor etc.</p>
<p>Now, first step I have done after downloading the tools is extracting the zip and starting the process explorer(inside the folder procexp). It show me all the running processes in the system.</p>
<p><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/imageedit_4_4535969268.png" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"></p>
<p>I click on options on the top bar and check the Verify image signature entry so that I can neglect the windows verified(code-signed) programs and only concentrate on not verified programs.<br>
Well, I have found two interesting non verified services running in the system.<br>
One is <em>isMiner</em> program running and using lots of cpu(You must have guessed its working just by looking at its name).<br>
Other is some random named program “<em>2e4e333….</em>&quot; (which looks like some hash value). It also got a little suspicious icon which takes my attention.<br>
Before going further on any discussion I must need to know for sure that these are the program causing trouble. One thing I am sure about is if they are any type of malware then they must try to persist themselves in the system. For that windows applications add autorun entries key on the registry. So I started the Autoruns tool present in sysinternals toolset. Then I try to find out the entries for both of these programs and successfully found that somewhere down.<br>
There is a tick box before their names, showing if these autorun is enabled or not. So, I disable both of them.</p>
<p><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/image1.PNG" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"><br>
<img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/image2.PNG" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"></p>
<blockquote>
<p><em><strong>Note</strong></em>: I can also delete these entries by right click→ select Delete, but it is recommended that you just turn off these autoruns because the program running for these entries maybe get triggered when those registry keys are deleted and it add them back again.<em>Hope that make sense!</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>You can easily argue for now that these program maybe some legitimate programs used by some other process. So, I finally need to confirm that these are the malwares running there.<br>
For that I right click on both entries and select ‘<em>jump to image</em>’. It takes me to the location of executable saved for these programs. One of them is at User→ AppData→ Roaming (which is a common place malware put their executable for autorun on system startup)</p>
<p><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/image3.PNG" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"><br>
other was inside C:\→ Program files.</p>
<p>I copy all the executables and place them inside some known location. Next step is to check if these program are really dangerous or not. For that I went to a website called virustotal.com. VirusTotal(owned by google)  analyze suspicious files and URLs to detect types of malware including viruses, worms, and trojans.<br>
First I uploaded isMiner.exe.</p>
<p><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/virustotal1.png" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"></p>
<p>You can see that it is detected by <em>44/65</em> antivirus programs. You can easy guess that it is a Bitcoin miner program that uses your cpu power to mine bitcoins. It is also the cause of high power consumption by your system and even slow performance sometimes.</p>
<p><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/isminer2.png" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"></p>
<p>There is another file named <em>xmrig.exe</em> there which is the file generated by <em>isMiner.exe</em> for its working.<br>
Analyzing that shows detection ratio <em>47/67</em>.<br>
Now lets upload the another suspicious program.</p>
<p><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/exe2.png" alt="Finding and removing malware from windows in minimal steps using sysinternals suite"></p>
<p>Well, it got detected by 13 /67 antiviruses means it is quite good at hiding itself.<br>
With a little static analysis I was able to find out that it is a adware(also can be confirm using virustotal report). Then I run it inside a sandboxed environment and found that it show large ads banner on every browser’s page. So, the firefox error about not secure connection is causing by this program only since it monitor all the pages you browse and shows ads on them.</p>
<p>So It was confirmed that both of these program are the malwares affecting the system. I delete both of them(registry keys are already disabled) and restarted the system. And as you can imagine after next reboot all those issues are gone and the system became normal again.</p>
<p>So, thats it for this post. In future article I will show you how I reverse engineer these malware and we also look into how to use other utility in sysinternals suite to find malwares.<em><strong>Stay tuned!</strong></em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Data Storage virtualization in Linux (Part 1)]]></title><description><![CDATA[Learn how to use file storage in Staas services. In file storage we create a file and use it as our virtual partition then format it in desire file system and mount it. All the operation we do in our real disk partition(*/dev/sda*) can be done on that with some little tricks or manipulation.]]></description><link>https://shubham0d.github.io/data-storage-virtualization-in-linux/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a43fad3c053a010ef42b2e2</guid><category><![CDATA[Virtualization]]></category><category><![CDATA[Linux]]></category><category><![CDATA[Cloud computing]]></category><category><![CDATA[Tutorial]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Shubham Dubey]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 20:30:41 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/14.PNG" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/14.PNG" alt="Data Storage virtualization in Linux (Part 1)"><p>We can't deny the fact that traditional model of data management and hosting has been changed and user want their data/resources to be centralized and much flexible. By the innovation of virtualization technology it is become much more easier for large organization and even small businesses to centralized not only their storage but also every other thing they came across in IT world. But due to rapid increase in structured and non-structured data, a nice management for storage is required and resources have not to be wasted.</p>
<p>If we talk about storage as a service(Staas) in cloud computing, if you are a cloud service provider then lots of your resources get wasted since once you allocate a fix storage space to any client, its lots of part get useless since he never use them at once and you are not allowed to allocate them to others. To solve or minimize problem like that, it will be a good initiative to use file data storage as shared storage solution rather then object storage or storage attached network (SAN).<br>
In this article I will try to get you through step by step procedure of using and managing file storage solution and also uses of <em>qemu-img</em> virtualization. I will even try to get you through some new techniques/operations of disk virtualization which can be really useful at some point to your cloud server.<br>
I have used all simple techniques which can be easily understandable and are not so eye catching but will really help you at different level of storage system development and management.</p>
<p><strong>Note:</strong><br>
All tools used are generally available on most on the linux system, if not then can be easily downloadable via your default online repository. The tested system for these commands is <em>RHEL 7.0</em> but they will work on other linux system in same way or with little steps rearrangements.</p>
<h2 id="whatisfilestorage">What is file storage?</h2>
<p>If you are a Staas provider you will one day definitely come across a problem that lots of your storage actually get wasted since if a user purchases 10GB of storage space from you,then you are forced to allocate him his 10GB regardless of the fact that he not gonna use all of his space at once. Another frequent problem can be if your data storage have 100 GB storage left and you are thinking to buy new storage disk in few days. If in the mean time if someone unexpectedly demands you 200 GB storage then you have to refuse him to provide that. But a good provider is which who fulfill all users  requests and provide 24/7 service. So a better solution for that is to use file storage. Through file storage you can scale your storage according to data inside it and even allocate that much of space which you even don't have.</p>
<p>File Storage are rely on the fact that everything in your operating system is a file. In file storage we create a file and use it as our virtual partition then format it in desire file system and mount it. All the operation we do in our real disk partition(<em>/dev/sda</em>) can be done on that with some little tricks or manipulation. For this procedure we use sparse images as our disks file.</p>
<h3 id="sowhataresparsefile">So, what are sparse file?</h3>
<p>A sparse file is a specific type of file which aims to use file system space more efficiently by using metadata to represent empty blocks. In the case of a sparse file, blocks are allocated and written dynamically as the actual data is written, rather than at the time the file is created. So the point is if you create a 10Gb sparse file it will not even take 1Mb of your disk space but its property info will show 10GB as it is the allocated space.So lets start the procedure we need to follow with spase file.</p>
<p>A sparse file can be created by either using <em>truncate</em> or <em>dd</em> utility in linux (another tools are also available).</p>
<pre><code>$truncate --size=1GB test.img
</code></pre>
<p>This will create a 1Gb sparse image <em>test.img</em>. To get same result with dd use</p>
<pre><code>$dd if=/dev/zero of=test.img bs=1024 count=0 seek=$[1024*1000]
</code></pre>
<p>here <em>bs</em> is block size and size is provided by <em>seek</em>, you can also use this for simplicity</p>
<pre><code>$dd if=/dev/zero of=test.img bs=1 count=0 seek=1G
</code></pre>
<p>if you want to allocate the whole disk space at once(which is not a good solution in our case) then you can use <em>fallocate</em> for that</p>
<pre><code>$fallocate -l 1G test.img
</code></pre>
<blockquote>
<p><em><strong>A little fun trick:</strong></em><br>
Can I create a 2TB partition on my 1Tb hard disk?<br>
the ans is yes!.Since sparse file have property to not take the space while creation hence you can use them to do that</p>
<pre><code>$truncate –size=2TB mylargefile.img
</code></pre>
<p>create any desired file system on it</p>
<pre><code>$mkfs.ext2 mylargefile.img
$mount mylargefile.img /mnt/
</code></pre>
<p>now you have a 2Tb partition which you can show to your techie friend to impress. :p</p>
</blockquote>
<p>After creating the file you can format it and directly mount it to use as your storage but to make it possible to do lots of disk operations, it first have to connect to loop device using <em>losetup</em> utility. To attach the file to your loop device use</p>
<pre><code>$losetup -f test.img
</code></pre>
<p>were <em>test.img</em> is your formated file. To see all such file or block device connected to loop device use</p>
<pre><code>$losetup -a
</code></pre>
<p>you can easily <em>grep</em> the last created loop device by</p>
<pre><code>$losetup -a | tail -1
</code></pre>
<p>After creating the loop device its time to format it. You can use any file system but my recommendation is using ext2 file system(the reason will be explained later).<br>
To formate use <em>mkfs</em> utils</p>
<pre><code>$mkfs.ext2 /dev/loop0
</code></pre>
<p>If you are working on big data management then <em>xfs filesystem</em> have to be preferred because it works well on handling large file and support larger inode data.<br>
Now you can mount your formatted loop device to use as your virtual storage to share</p>
<pre><code>$mount /dev/loop0 /mnt/
</code></pre>
<p>To share it across network using service like nfs,open <em>/etc/exports</em> add this entry</p>
<pre><code>$cat /etc/exports
/mnt/	*(rw,rsync,no_root_squash)
</code></pre>
<p>close it and restart the <em>nfs</em> service by</p>
<pre><code>$service nfsd restart
</code></pre>
<p>once you put the data inside the device you can check its original occupied size by using <em>qemu-img</em> utility</p>
<pre><code>$qemu-img info test.img
</code></pre>
<p>or by <em>du</em> command</p>
<pre><code>$du -h test.img
</code></pre>
<p>Since our file storage is ready, in next part we will look into common disk operations you can do with file storage.<em>Stay tuned!</em></p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Finding file information using different methods]]></title><description><![CDATA[Information about files content can be found using different methods in both windows and linux systems. This knowledge can be handy if you are developing a program or script that is dealing with files.]]></description><link>https://shubham0d.github.io/finding-file-information-using-different-methods/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a43858e98308b0f6c141754</guid><category><![CDATA[Tutorial]]></category><category><![CDATA[Analysis]]></category><category><![CDATA[Linux]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Shubham Dubey]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 12:06:35 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/file-types-.png.jpeg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="kg-card-markdown"><h1 id="1findingfileinformationusingextensions">1) Finding file information using extensions</h1>
<br>
A common way to analysis the detail of a file is using the extensions of the file. Extension is a set of characters at the end of the file name
separated by the final dot(.) from the filename.
<blockquote>
<img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/file-types-.png.jpeg" alt="Finding file information using different methods"><p><strong>Example</strong>: In a file with name “<em>dolphin.jpg</em>”, dolphin is the name of file whereas jpg is the file extension which tells the file type is actually a <em>image/jpeg</em> file.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="usingextensionsdetailtofindfileinfo">Using extensions detail to find file info</h2>
<p>In linux based systems the filetype info through extension is stored on location <em>/usr/share/misc/magic</em> as a structure whereas same information can be found on windows registry at <em>HKEYCLASSESROOT</em> subtree.<br>
<em>Given below is the part of linux filetype structure</em>:</p>
<pre><code>  text/html                             html htm shtml;
  text/css                              css;
  text/xml                              xml rss;
  image/gif                             gif;
  image/jpeg                            jpeg jpg;
  application/x-javascript              js;
  text/plain                            txt;
  text/x-component                      htc;
  text/mathml                           mml;
  image/png                             png;
  image/x-icon                          ico;
  image/x-jng                           jng;
  image/vnd.wap.wbmp                    wbmp;
  application/java-archive              jar war ear;
  application/mac-binhex40              hqx;
  application/pdf                       pdf;
  application/x-cocoa                   cco;
  application/x-java-archive-diff       jardiff;
  application/x-java-jnlp-file          jnlp;
  application/x-makeself                run;
  application/x-perl                    pl pm;
  application/x-pilot                   prc pdb;
  application/x-rar-compressed          rar;
  application/x-redhat-package-manager  rpm;
  application/x-sea                     sea;
  application/x-shockwave-flash         swf;
  application/x-stuffit                 sit;
  application/x-tcl                     tcl tk;
  application/x-x509-ca-cert            der pem crt;
  application/x-xpinstall               xpi;
  application/zip                       zip;
  application/octet-stream              deb;
  application/octet-stream              bin exe dll;
  application/octet-stream              dmg;
  application/octet-stream              eot;
  application/octet-stream              iso img;
  application/octet-stream              msi msp msm;
  audio/mpeg                            mp3;
  audio/x-realaudio                     ra;
  video/mpeg                            mpeg mpg;
  video/quicktime                       mov;
  video/x-flv                           flv;
  video/x-msvideo                       avi;
  video/x-ms-wmv                        wmv;
  video/x-ms-asf                        asx asf;
  video/x-mng                           mng;
</code></pre>
<p>Advantage of using these sources is reliability as they are stored by operating system default itself and its also easy to use and handle across different programs.<br>
The issue with getting dependent on file extension is that extensions are a convention that are not enforced by the file system or OS. A user can change a extension and the file can still be used by programs.</p>
<h1 id="2findingfileinformationusingmagicnumber">2) Finding file information using magic number</h1>
<p>Much reliable way to find any file details can be using Header signature of a file.<br>
Typically file header contains metadata about the file to help a software application validate the file content is correct or not, load the data and view or process the data. Header signature or also called magic number typically are at the start of the file and allows a program to initially determine if the file is valid by first checking presence of number.<br>
Often quoted example is JPEG byte sequence <em>0xFF 0xD8 0xFF 0xE0</em>, appear as the characters <em>ÿØÿà</em> when JPEG file viewed in a hex/ASCII editor.</p>
<p><img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/xxd-2.png" alt="Finding file information using different methods"></p>
<p>Using these magic number has advantage over using file extension as these number produce accurate result of file type. Manipulating these number will result the file to be not identified by application that will process it.</p>
<h2 id="usingmagicnumbertofindfileinfo">Using magic number to find file info</h2>
<p>You can get hexadecimal magic number of a program using any hexeditor tool in linux or windows system. For example in linux system you can use xxd as you hex editor.</p>
<pre><code>$xxd filename
</code></pre>
<p>Once you find the magic number you can compare them with the magic numbers of different format.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You can also use file command (which exatly done the same to find the file<br>
type using magic numbers).<br>
<img src="https://shubham0d.github.io/content/images/2017/12/fileCommand.png" alt="Finding file information using different methods"></p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="3findingfileinformationbyanalysingthecontaininsidethefile">3) Finding file information by analysing the contain inside the file</h1>
<p>Most of the file we deal in real are text based(containing ASCII characters).<br>
A text based file can be analysed by looking at its content.For example for programming files we can look at the header at the starting of code to find the programming language used. All programing code has includes at the starting of program in their defined format or have shebang <em>‘#!/bin/program’</em> at the start.</p>
<pre><code>#include&lt;stduo.h&gt;                        C/C++
#!/bin/bash                              Bash executable file
#!/bin/sh                                sh executable
#!/bin/perl                              perl program
#!/bin/ruby                              ruby program
&lt;?xml version=&quot;1.0&quot; encoding=&quot;UTF-8&quot;?&gt;   xml file
etc
</code></pre>
<p>For configuration file we can look for the syntax type used by common<br>
formats like <em>yml</em>,<em>ini</em> or <em>xml</em>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For example we can look for name=value field in case of ini config files.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These header are processed by programs to find how to treat these file or<br>
through which compiler to run these file. Hence they are mostly included in<br>
fix formatted files and we can use them to get desirable file info.</p>
</div>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>